字幕转制｜天外生物
感谢原字幕制作者
谁？
Who's there?
- 是我，梅  - 呀，梅！我来开门
- It's Mui.  - I'll let you in.
进来吧
Come in.
跟我来
Follow me.
青木瓜之味
THE SCENT OF GREEN PAPAYA
一九五一年，越南西贡
是小梅，我们新来的丫头
It's Mui, our new servant.
走了一整天的路，把她累坏了
Poor thing, she walked all day to get here.
桃如果还没死，也应该有她那般大
If Tho were still alive, she'd be about Mui's age.
我们不要说这个了
Don't talk about her.
也许她现在很好呢！
She may be better off where she is now...
快要宵禁了，忠还没回来
It's almost curfew and Trung isn't home yet.
妈要睡了
Mother is getting ready for bed.
我上去帮她
I'll go see if she needs anything.
- 呀，忠…  - 爸，你还没睡？
- Ah, Trung!  - Still up, Dad?
再睡会，少奶说的
The mistress says you can sleep in.
我会叫醒你生火
I'll wake you up to make the fire.
记住，油一定要烧热
Remember, for this dish, the fat needs to be very hot.
菜要这样炒
When you sauté the vegetables,
这样炒才入味
brown them a little for added flavor.
不能炒太久，否则就不爽口
Don't overcook them, they'll go mushy.
菜先放一旁
Then put them to one side.
肉也用同样方法炒
The same goes for the meat, let the fat burn. Here.
把水倒进去
Put it in the water.
猪油可让菜发亮
You need a bit of fat to make the vegetables shiny.
显得好看一些
The dishes must look beautiful.
不管好不好看，我们都会吃下去
For us peasants, beautiful or not, it ends up in our bellies.
但主人们可不一样
But our masters aren't like us. When the meat is done,
煮好后…
add the vegetables.
把菜分成两碟
Then put half on each plate.
一份送到楼下，一份给姥姥
One for downstairs, and one for the grandmother.
别忘记给我们自己留一份
Don't forget to keep some for us.
听，姥姥念完经了
She's finished praying.
做菜时，把蔬菜…
Time to serve. Put the vegetables...
放进滚水里
in the boiling water.
她是谁的母亲？
Is she the mistress's mother?
少奶的，洗洗手
The master's. Wash your hands.
少奶才生下来，她丈夫就死掉了
She lost her husband just after the master was born.
她现在整天都在楼上念经
Now she stays upstairs and spends all her time praying.
快用碗盛饭
Hurry up, put the rice in a big bowl.
- 都好了吗？  - 都好了
- Is everything ready?  - Yes...
梅，你来端姥姥那盘
Mui, take the grandmother's tray.
行，我来端这个吧
It's all right, I'll do it.
你端这个吧
Take this one, then.
爸，我跟浩仁在外面吃
Dad... Khuyen and I will eat outside.
你先小睡一会吧
After the meal, take your nap as usual.
我们会赶回来吃下午茶
We'll be back for tea. Is that all right?
好的
Yes, fine.
我呢？我可以去吗？
Can I have tea with you too?
不，你太小了
No, you're not old enough.
梅，来点汤
Mui, go fetch a bit more soup in the kitchen.
妈不想一个人吃
Mother doesn't want to eat alone,
想要你陪她吃饭
she wants you to keep her company.
- 好吧  - 我也要上去
- All right.  - I'll come too.
把这拿上楼
Take that upstairs.
快吃，又要迟到了
Eat quickly. You mustn't be late for school.
奶奶，现在放暑假，不用上课
I don't have school, Grandmother. It's the summer holidays.
噢，是的！
Ah, yes, so it is.
妈，我们走啦
Khuyen and I are going out.
我与浩仁会回来吃下午茶
We'll be back for tea. I already told Dad.
好的，我会买些蛋糕
Okay. I'll send Mui to buy cakes.
- 再见，伯母  - 再见
- Good-bye.  - Good-bye, Khuyen.
梅，你可以吃饭了
Mui, you can go and eat.
- 小蓝，快吃  - 妈，好吃
- Lam, eat, my child.  - Bon appétit, Mommy.
这个给你，吃吧
Your bowl is there. Take some meat.
没汤了！真是的！
There's no more soup, it's really annoying.
我们都分出去了，给了楼上楼下
When everyone eats in a different place,
盘子都光了，没剩下
the dishes get scattered and we get nothing.
然后，把盘子洗干净
When you've finished, do the washing-up.
跟忠先生一起的男人是谁？
Who was that with Mr. Trung?
那是浩仁少爷，忠先生的朋友
Mr. Khuyen, Mr. Trung's friend.
快吃
Eat.
天！
Tin!
谢谢！再见！
Thank you, good-bye.
再见！
Good-bye, thank you very much.
梅，把手洗干净，去买十块饼
Wash your hands, then go buy some cakes.
是！少奶
Yes, madam.
如果你喜欢，三个月后
If you like, after the holidays,
你可以回家探望你娘
you can go to visit your mother.
谢谢少奶
Thank you, madam.
梅，快！该生火了
Mui! Hurry up, it's time to light the fire.
小女孩
Little one! Please...
你叫什么？
What's your name?
我叫梅
Mui.
啊！你就是梅…我叫唐
So your name's Mui, is it? I'm Thuan.
是时候念经了
It's time for the grandmother's prayers.
姥姥好吗？
Is she all right?
她很好
Yes, she's fine.
这样就好了
That's excellent.
很好
Excellent.
谢谢你，小梅
Thank you, little Mui.
- 再见  - 再见，唐先生
- Good-bye.  - Good-bye, Mr. Thuan.
- 你去哪儿？  - 呼吸点新鲜空气
- Where are you going?  - Out for a walk.
是的，天这么热，很难入睡
Good idea. It isn't easy sleeping in this heat.
小心宵禁
Be careful, it's almost curfew.
真热死人！
It's so hot!
天！真热死人！
My God, it's so hot!
你可以明天再收拾东西
Leave your things for tonight, put them away tomorrow.
你今天够累的了
You've worked enough for today.
休息吧
Rest.
你的父母呢？
Tell me about your family.
你有兄弟姊妹吗？
Do you have brothers or sisters?
我爸三年前死了
My father died three years ago.
妈妈跟姐姐在乡下
My mother stayed in the village with my little sister.
你什么时候回去看她们？
When will you see your mother?
少奶说三个月后
The mistress said after the holidays
我可以回家探望妈
I could go back.
这就好，少奶是个好人
Ah, that's good. The mistress is kind.
我之前谁在这里睡？
Who used to sleep here?
另一个丫头
A servant, like you and me.
她回家嫁人去了
She went home to get married.
神位那幅照片的人是姥姥的丈夫？
Is the man in the photo the grandmother's husband?
是的
Yes.
他死时还很年青
He died at a very young age.
那小女孩是谁？
And who's the little girl?
说起来很凄凉
It's a sad story.
她是少爷和少奶的女儿
She was the master's daughter.
她叫桃
Her name was Tho.
七年前死了
She died seven years ago.
如果她还活着，应该跟你一样大
If she were still alive, she'd be about your age.
她是怎样死的？
How did she die?
病死的，但少爷总觉得是他的错
From an illness, but the master blames himself.
为什么？
How come?
七年前…
About seven years ago,
少爷拿着所有钱离开了家
the master left home with all the family's savings.
这已经是他第三次这样做
It was the third time I'd seen him abandon his home and family.
这之前，他花光了钱
Once he'd spent all the money on women,
便会回家
he would come home.
但这次，他走了很长一段时间
But this time he went away for longer than usual.
这之前他每次回家…
When he came home the other times,
少奶什么都没说？
didn't the mistress say anything?
对，一句话也没说
Nothing, not even a word.
她很开心，喜极而泣
She was so happy she cried.
桃呢？她怎样了？
And what happened to Tho?
又宵禁了…
There's the curfew.
那边有些动静
Just when it was getting cool.
应该是少爷回来了
The master must be home by now.
他离家三星期后…
Three weeks after the master left,
桃生病了
Tho fell ill.
在他回家前一天
The day before her father returned,
她便死了
she died.
他一定是觉得她的死…
The master must have thought she died
是为了要惩罚他犯的罪
in order to pay for his sins.
所以他之后再也没有离家过
That's why he never goes out now.
好了，睡觉吧
Right, let's get some sleep.
明天还要早起呢！
We have to get up early tomorrow.
妈妈！
Mom!
起来！是时候了
Mui, it's time to get up.
你很幸运
You're lucky.
你这个年纪还可以做些好梦
At your age, you still have good dreams.
- 你梦见什么？  - 我不知道
- What did you dream about?  - I don't know.
老天爷，我真想做梦
Have you forgotten?
我不知有多久没做梦了
I'd love to dream, but I haven't dreamt for years.
来吧，洗脸去！
Come on, let's go and wash.
有一些日子…我醒来时
Some mornings I wake up
脑海里总是记得一名老妇
with the image of an old woman in my head.
也许那是我夜里作的梦
I don't know if it's a dream.
我不知道那老妇是我的母亲…
I don't know if the old woman is my mother
抑或是我自己
or if it's me.
天，谁这么早就在厨房？
Who's up at such an early hour?
少奶，这么早就起来？
Mistress, you're up early!
- 还有米吗？  - 只够四至五天
- Do we have any rice?  - Only enough for five days.
这些给你拿到市场去变卖，要确保以后几天有足够吃的
Here's the market money. Do the best you can.
梅，看看这些耳环
Mui, see these earrings?
少爷又带着所有钱出走了！我的天！
This means the master's left with the family money again.
让我们把牙齿刷干净
We brush our teeth, teeth, teeth
把脸、手、脚都洗干净
Wash our hands and feet, feet, feet
把头发梳好
Then we comb our hair, hair, hair
还有别忘了上厕所
And remember to poo, poo, poo
不，这匹也不要
No, I don't like that either.
对不起…
I'm so sorry.
- 不要紧，再见  - 再见
- Never mind, thank you.  - Good-bye.
你怎么了？
What happened to you?
打架了
I had a fight.
跟谁？
With whom?
那些小孩
The other children.
他们有打伤你吗？
Did they hurt you?
爸在家吗？
Is Daddy back?
不，不在家
No, not yet.
去梅那里换些干净衣服
Ask Mui to give you some clean clothes.
如果菜不够的话…
When there isn't much food, make it salty.
多加些盐，这样
That way they'll eat more rice with the dishes.
他们便会多吃些饭
Give me the bowl.
这些放煮好的米
It's for the boiled vegetables.
把这个拿上楼
Take this upstairs.
妈说先吃
Mommy told us to start.
太咸了！
Yuck! It's too salty.
看！
Look.
快吃
Eat!
好吃吗？
Is it good?
小梅…来，我想问你一些事情
Mui, come here. I've something to ask you.
谢谢你，唐先生
Thank you, Mr. Thuan.
姥姥好吗？
Is Grandmother well?
我们快没有米了
There's hardly any rice left.
我们一匹布也没卖出去
We didn't sell any cloth today.
只卖了两捆棉花…
Just a few shirt buttons.
那点钱可以买些什么呢？
What can we buy with the money from a few buttons?
老天爷！
God!
都是你的错
It's your fault.
要是你懂得怎样爱他，他便不会找别的女人
If you'd shown him love, he wouldn't have taken mistresses.
我一开始就知道
I knew right from the start.
我的儿子跟你不会开心
I knew my son would be unhappy with you.
你有一个丈夫…但你根本不知道怎样讨他开心
You don't know how to make your husband happy.
好了，够了
Okay, that's enough.
剩下来的木瓜怎么办？
What do I do with the rest of the papaya?
把它扔掉
Throw it away.
够了
Stop that!
把这个拿上去
Take this.
好了，你可以去吃饭了
That's fine. You can go eat.
慢慢吃，妈
Bon appétit, Mommy.
爸什么时候回来？
Mommy, when will Daddy be home?
我不知道，快吃
I don't know. Now eat.
你为什么哭？
Why are you crying like that?
为什么爸不回来？
Where's Daddy? Why doesn't he come home?
闭嘴！
Shut up!
- 谢谢  - 哪里，再见！
- Thank you.  - Good-bye.
再见！谢谢
Good-bye, thank you.
有买米的钱了
Now we've got money for rice.
去买二十五公斤的米回来
Go buy 25 kilos of rice.
快！我们要切肉了
Mui, quick, the meat needs cutting.
那儿…放那儿
There, put it there.
这米很好！
It's very good rice.
- 我们今晚有客人  - 谁？
- We have a guest tonight.  - Who?
浩仁先生
Mr. Khuyen.
浩仁先生是谁？
Who's Mr. Khuyen?
忠先生的朋友呀！
Why, Mr. Trung's friend!
我可以试试自己炒菜吗？
Can I do the sautéed vegetables by myself?
好吧，你试试
Yes, if you like.
她丈夫死后三年…
Even three years after her husband died,
她仍然不接受我
she still didn't want me.
她依然深爱着他
I realized that she still loved him
怎么也不肯与我结婚
and didn't want to become my wife.
自那天开始
Since then, whenever I've been able,
我便一直在远处看着她
I've watched her from afar.
她搬过好几次，我一直跟着她走
She's moved house several times. I've always followed her.
所以我与你才得以认识
That's how you and I were able to meet.
自桃死后
Since Tho, her granddaughter, died,
姥姥便一直未下过楼
Grandmother hasn't been downstairs.
我已有七年没看见过她
I haven't seen her for seven years.
告诉我，小梅
Tell me, may
你可以让她下来院子走走…
Couldn't you get her to come down into the courtyard,
让我看见她一面吗？
so I can see her?
你为什么不上去见她
Why don't you go up to see her?
你躲起来，她当然见不到你
You could hide and see her, without her seeing you.
不，不可能的
No, it's impossible.
如果她看见了我，事情可糟了
It'd be terrible if she saw me.
不，不可能的
It's impossible.
走！上去！
Go on, go up.
不要紧
It doesn't matter.
老天！
Oh, my God!
少奶最喜欢这些花瓶
You don't know how fond the mistress is of her vases.
他们是老古董
They're very old.
我一生赚的钱也不够买一个
Even with all my savings, I couldn't afford them.
你真幸运
You're lucky.
少奶，快起来
Quick, madam, come quickly!
这东西一对才值钱，没有另一个一毛钱也不值
It's a very valuable piece, but only with its twin.
你拿主意
It's up to you.
好的，就卖吧
All right, I accept.
忠，快！
Trung, quick!
十年后
10 YEARS LATER
梅
Mui!
快，我妈想见你
Hurry up, my mother wants a word.
生意不好已经有一阵子
Business has been bad for a while.
这样下去会出问题的
If things don't change, we'll have real problems.
天井没什么用
We don't use the inner courtyard.
可用来再养一些鹦鹉
I was wondering about rearing animals in it to supplement our income.
嗯，再说吧…
Yes. We'll see.
那样的话，我再四处问问
I n that case, I'll get some advice tomorrow.
妈正跟梅在说这事
Mother's going to speak to Mui.
梅要是跟了你的朋友浩仁，日子会好过许多
I'm sure she won't be unhappy at your friend Khuyen's.
他一个人住，只爱写曲
He lives alone and composes music.
他几乎不回这边的家
He's hardly ever home.
他父母很有钱，梅在他那儿会好过点
His parents are rich, she'll be better paid there.
如果桃仍在世，我会把这些给她
These are things I would have given to Tho if she had lived.
谢谢你，十年来，我仿佛有一个女儿在身旁
For ten years, thanks to you, I've felt that I have a daughter.
我从没意识到，但有你在我感到很安慰
Without knowing it, you've really comforted me.
小蓝走了，他需要一个写作的地方
Lam has gone.
现在你也要离开了
He needs a quiet place to write his books.
很长一段时间里…
And now you're leaving.
我希望小蓝会娶你
For years I hoped Lam would take you for his wife.
我的女儿…我的小女儿
Mui, my little girl!
不要吃！带我上餐馆
Don't eat, take me out to dinner.
你写了多少？
Have you made any progress?
把你写的曲奏给我听
Play me what you've composed.
闻着好香
That smells good.
好吗？
Well?
- 你新来的女仆怎么样？  - 不错
- Your new servant?  - All right.
什么叫“不错”？
What does "all right" mean?
她很勤快
That she works hard.
我不是问你这个！算了
That wasn't what I was asking, but it doesn't matter.
- 我给你的花瓶呢？  - 破了
- Where's the vase I gave you?  - It's broken.
破了？你是说，她把它打破了？
Broken? She broke it, you mean.
若我说她故意这样做，你会怎么说？
If I said it was deliberate, what would you reply?
我怀疑越南会有多少女人…
I wonder how many women in Vietnam
摸过她们未婚夫的头
have never touched their fiancé's head.
我母亲告诉过我，她们都会教导女儿
My mother told me little girls used to be taught
一个受过良好教育的女人不会这样做
that a well-bred woman shouldn't.
她也说你已经有两个多星期
She also said it's nearly two weeks
没去看他们了
since you last visited us.
你父亲也有点惊讶
Your father is surprised too.
“在我的园子里…
"I n my garden
有一棵木瓜树
"there is a papaya tree.
那些木瓜一串串地吊在树上
"The papayas grow in bunches.
熟透了的木瓜有一种淡黄的色泽
"Ripe papayas are a pale yellow.
它们是…
"They are...
它们是芳香的
"They are fragrant
味道甜丝丝的”
"and they taste very sweet."
“我们养了一只黑色的狗
"For the past two years
已经有两年了
"we have had a black dog.
它的身子很长
"He has a very long body.
长了一双大脚
"He has long legs
还有一双大耳朵”
"and big ears."
我开始了，好吗？
I'll start, all right?
“泉水从石头缝里汩汩地流出来
"The spring water, filling a hole in the rock,
被拨弄时闪闪发光
"trembles gently.
地层的颤动使海水产生波涛
"The vibration of the ground gave rise to powerful waves
互相撞击而生出滚滚大浪
"that spread across the surface in an irregular pattern,
汹涌彭湃，永无休止
"without breaking.
如果有个动词的意思是‘和谐地运动’
"If there's a verb meaning to stir harmoniously,
用在这里再合适不过了
"it should be used here.
樱桃树树影婆娑
"Plunged into darkness, the cherry trees
灿烂的盛放…
"unfurl and sway and bend
随着海浪的节奏轻轻摆动
"to the rhythm of the water.
但最有趣的是，不论怎样变化…
"But what's interesting is that, however they change,
它们仍保持着樱桃树的形状”
"they still resemble cherry trees."
Subtitles - Susannah Rooke for TELETOTA